Guide to the Coeducation Collection 1871-1998
Coeducation Collection1871 July 19-1998 Dec 4
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University
1000-88
0.6
2
Wesleyan University went through two phases of coeducation, the first of which lasted from 1872 to 1909, and the second from 1970 to the present. In the first phase, women represented a small minority of the undergraduate community, and only forty-three women graduated in the period from 1872 and 1892. However, female admissions increased in 1898, which led to a corresponding decrease in male admissions. From 1900 onward, the decline in Wesleyan's overall admissions contributed to the movement against coeducation, as many feared that the college had become too "feminized." In 1909, the Board of Trustees decided to end coeducation at Wesleyan, which would remain an all-male institution until 1970.
The Coeducation Collection includes notes, letters, records, clippings, photographs, and meeting transcripts from Wesleyan University's first phase of coeducation (1872-1909). These materials date from 1871 to 1998. The entire collection has been digitized and individual documents and photographs may be accessed by clicking on the links.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Historical Note
Founded as a men's college in 1831, Wesleyan University went through two phases of coeducation, the first of which lasted from 1872 to 1909, and the second from 1970 to the present. The 1872 decision to admit women resulted partly from Wesleyan's concession, as a Methodist institution, to the well-established Methodist practice of educating men and women together. In addition, seven other New England institutions had initiated proposals to coeducate in 1871, which may have encouraged Wesleyan to do the same. These proposals, while not formally coordinated, all came in response to the women's suffrage movement of the early 1870s.
Wesleyan's first female class had four members: Jennie Larned, Phebe Almeda Stone, Angie Villette Warren, and Hannah Ada Taylor. From 1872 until 1892, women represented a small minority of the undergraduate community, and only forty-three women graduated in that period. However, female admissions increased in 1898, which led to a decrease in male admissions; this development fueled the fears of those who believed that the presence of women at Wesleyan would curtail opportunities for male students.
The shift away from coeducation was sparked by a change in the leadership of the trustees. Trustee Stephen Henry Olin led Wesleyan's movement away from Methodism and its redefinition as a metropolitan-based university, with a heavy emphasis on athletics. This shift would align Wesleyan more closely with the values of all-male institutions such as Amherst, Williams and Yale.
From 1900 onward, the decline in Wesleyan's overall admissions contributed to the movement against coeducation, as many feared that the college had become too "feminized." Starting in 1900, the admission of women was capped at 20 percent, but this measure never fully reassured coeducation's opponents. The trustees' decision to end coeducation in 1909 came as the culmination of a decades-long backlash against the 1872 decision. Last-ditch efforts to found a separate college for women gained momentum in 1907, but they failed to generate the necessary revenue, and the effort was eventually abandoned. Under the leadership of alumna Elizabeth C. Wright, class of 1897, a committee was formed to consider other options. This effort eventuated in the founding of Connecticut College for Women, which opened in New London, Connecticut, in 1915.
Collection Overview
The Coeducation Collection includes notes, letters, records, clippings, photographs, and meeting transcripts from Wesleyan University's first phase of coeducation (1872-1909).
The entire collection has been digitized and individual documents and photographs may be accessed by clicking on the "View" links in Detailed Description of the Collection below. The digitized files may also be accessed by clicking this link: Wesleyan University: Coeducation at Wesleyan, 1867-1912 collection in Shared Shelf Commons.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Women college students.; Women--Education (Higher).; Coeducation.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.
Related Material
Knight, Louise Wilby, The "Quails": the history of Wesleyan University's first period of coeducation 1872-1912, honors thesis, 1972.
Guide to the Louise Wilby Knight Papers, 1971-1972
Delegard, Kirstin Thesis Research Notes, 1989-1990
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Records, 1871 July 19-1998 Dec 4, 2 boxes
  To view a digitized copy, click on the "View" link. The digitized files may also be accessed by clicking on this link: Wesleyan University: Coeducation at Wesleyan, 1867-1912 collection in Shared Shelf Commons.
  - List of sources of information (1872-1886) on coeducation at Wesleyan University (Box 1, Folder 1)
    View PDF.
  - List of sources of information (1900-1909) on coeducation at Wesleyan University, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List of sources of information (1972-1976) on coeducation at Wesleyan University (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Council minutes (1907-1908) on the formation of a co-ordinate college for women, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - J.M. Buckley, H.C.M. Ingraham, W.V. Kelley, and J.M. King. Statement on women students (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Walter N. Hill, class of 1901, to his grandmother, Catherine R.C. Smith. Letter on coeducation, 1898 Dec 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Statistics on female students at Wesleyan University from 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Comparative statistics of males in higher education from 1870-1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Comparative statistics of male and female Wesleyan University graduates from 1876-1912, 1978 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anna Knowles Beebe, Jessie Johnson Murpy, Helen Gilbert Purdue, and Clara F. Sykes. Letter on questionnaire for Wesleyan University alumnae from the classes of 1896-1912, 1966 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Responses to questionnaire for Wesleyan University alumnae from the classes of 1896-1912, 1966 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum on early coeducation at Wesleyan University, 1989 Mar (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Excerpts of Joint Board minutes from 1867-1872, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rev. George Steele. Penciled memo that women "may avail themselves" of a Wesleyan education, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clara Van Vleck to Professor Crawford. Explanatory note on George Steele memo, 1931 Oct 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dr. Linsday. Penciled resolution prepared for the meeting of the Joint Board of Trustees and Visitors on 1871 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diana Silbergeld. "A History of Women at Wes," Wesleyan Argus, 1998 Dec 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees printed minutes, 3 copies, 1899 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Wesleyan University Bulletin, 1899 Nov (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of a Coeducational Committee Report from the Wesleyan Young Alumni Association of New York on Coeducation, presented to the Wesleyan University Board of Trustees in 1900 Jan, 1899 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Digest of the New York Young Alumni Report on Coeducation," Wesleyan Argus, 1900 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Follow-up piece on "New York Young Alumni Report on Coeducation," Wesleyan Argus, 1900 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees printed minutes, 1900 Mar 20 and 1900 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed draft of "Papers on the Relation of Wesleyan University to the Higher Education of Women," 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed modified draft of "Papers on the Relation of Wesleyan University to the Higher Education of Women," 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Handwritten proposal to establish a bona fide Women's College, 2 copies, 1900 Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Papers on the Relation of Wesleyan University to the Higher Education of Women," printed by order of the Board of Trustees, 1900 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Handwritten Majority Report submitted to the Board of Trustees, 2 copies, 1900 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Caroline Rice Crawford and Clara Van Vleck. "To the Women Graduates of Wesleyan University," 4 copies, 1900 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women graduates' protest presented to the Board of Trustees of Wesleyan University, 4 copies (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Caroline Rice Crawford and Clara Van Vleck. Letter from the Committee of the Middletown Alumnae to the Board of Trustees, 3 copies, 1900 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - H.D. Byrnes, H.A. Ingraham, R.W. Langford, F.H. Ryder, and P.J. Treat. Student petition to the Board of Trustees, 3 copies, 1900 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Seward V. Coffin, Herbert Welch, and C.T. Winchester. Joint Committee on the Higher Education of Women at Wesleyan to the Board of Trustees, 4 copies, 1900 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - J.M. Van Vleck. Joint Committee on the Higher Education of Women at Wesleyan to the Board of Trustees, 3 copies, 1900 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Caroline Rice Crawford and Clara Van Vleck. "To the Alumnae of Wesleyan University," 2 copies, 1900 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees printed minutes, 1908 June 22 and 1908 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wesleyan University Bulletin, 1909 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Female Education," College Argus (Vol. 4, No. 19), 1871 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "A Protest Against Mixed Colleges," College Argus (Vol. 5, No. 3), 1871 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "College a Place for Ladies," College Argus (Vol. 5, No. 4), 1871 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Place aux Dames," College Argus (Vol. 5, No. 5), 1871 Nov 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - College Argus, 1872 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Manners, Language, and Dress in College," College Argus (Vol. 5, No. 15), 1872 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Statement on coeducation at Wesleyan University, College Argus, 1873 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Wesleyan as a Female Seminary," College Argus (Vol. 6, No. 11), 1873 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Coeducation at Wesleyan," College Argus (Vol. 6, No. 16), 1873 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Olla Podrida, 1873 Mar (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Op-ed on coeducation, College Argus, 1875 Nov 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter to the editor on coeducation, College Argus (Vol. 10, No. 4), 1876 Nov 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - College Argus (Vol. 16, No. 6), 1882 Dec 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The Quail-roost Removed from Hamlin Street," College Argus, 1883 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Coeducation," Wesleyan Argus (Vol. 31, No. 24), 1898 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Our Ultimatum," Wesleyan Argus (Vol. 32, No. 4), 1898 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Coeducation," Wesleyan Argus (Vol. 33, No. 6), 1899 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "The November Bulletin," Wesleyan Argus (Vol. 33, No. 9), 1899 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter to the editor and "Our Attitude toward the NY Young Alumni Report," Wesleyan Argus (Vol. 33, No. 17), 1900 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Coeducation Again," Wesleyan Argus (Vol. 33, No. 20), 1900 Mar 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Some Ungallant Wesleyans: Why Miss Ellis Will Not Read the Poem Before the Boys on Class Day," The New York Sun, 1876 Dec 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Ladies at the University," Home Journal, 1883 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Coeducation at Wesleyan: Young Men Blacklist Their Women Fellow-Students," 1899? (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Coeducation Ended: Wesleyan University Will Separate Boys and Girls," The Boston Post, 1900 Mar 23? (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - J.M. Buckley, H.C.M. Ingraham, W.V. Kelley, and J.M. King. Copy of report on coeducation passed by the Board of Trustees, 1900 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Boycott of Women Wins at Wesleyan: Substantial Victory for the Opponents of Coeducation Wins at Middletown," Meriden Weekly Republican, 2 copies, 1907 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Oust Women at Wesleyan" and "Wesleyan Coed Enters Protest," 1909 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Coeds Tag Class of 1912" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, 1898 Oct 5-1898 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    View scrapbook originals (PDF).
    View photocopies of originals (PDF).
  - Wesleyan University 1890 Class Day Program, 1890 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation to a reception hosted by Wesleyan University alumnae and undergraduates, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation to a reception hosted by Wesleyan University alumnae and undergraduates, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation from the Young Women's Christian Association of Wesleyan University to a homemade candy sale, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation from the Young Women's Christian Association of Wesleyan University to scenes from "Crawford," 1905 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation from the undergraduate women of Wesleyan University, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation to Julia Brazos, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invitation to Julia Brazos to Katherine Tinker's speech on "The Child of Yesterday and Today in Literature," 1908 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Boycott of Women at Wesleyan Wins," 1907 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Postcard to Burton Hughes with painted image of Wesleyan woman on reverse, 1908 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wesleyan University Bulletin No. 44, 1909 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Pach Bros. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    View JPG.
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, De Lamater Artistic Photographer (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Imperial Photographic Studio (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Pach Bros. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Randall and Abbott (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Pach Bros. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Pach Bros. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Hardy (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Hardy (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Moreno and Loher (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, C. T. Stuart Photographist (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified portrait of woman, Teo Lansel (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women, Pach Bros., 1881-1882 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women (duplicate), Pach Bros., 1881-1882 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women (duplicate), Pach Bros., 1881-1882 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women, 1882-1883 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women, Pach Bros., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women (duplicate), Pach Bros., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Group photo of Wesleyan women (Sarah Abbott, Lena Adams, Caroline Robbins, Clara Davis, Eva Dilks, Mary O'Flaherty, Alice Fuller, Christine Glover, Florence Graves, Isabel Graves, Lillian Hart, Martha Hills, Susan-Jane Mantle, Vida Moore, Maud Muzzy, Ellen Peck, Georgia Pottle, Lizzy Rice, and Marie Strobridge), Partridge, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    View front of photograph (JPG).
    View back of photograph (PDF).
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women, Waldon Smith, 1891-1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women (duplicate), Waldon Smith, 1891-1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified group photo of Wesleyan women, Pach Bros., 1896-1897 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Partially identified group photo of Wesleyan alumnae (Clara Angus, Margaret Crawford, and Agnes Thompson), 1910 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Partially identified group photo of Wesleyan alumnae in cap and gown (Clara Angus, Margaret Crawford, and Agnes Thompson), 1910 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified stereograph photo of men and women exiting Memorial Chapel, Strohmeyer and Wyman Publishers (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified stereograph photo of women in front of Webb Hall, Strohmeyer and Wyman Publishers, 1900 Oct 18 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photograph of an unidentified stereograph photo of men and women exiting Memorial Chapel and unidentified stereograph photo of a group of women in front of Webb Hall (scanned duplicates), Strohmeyer and Wyman Publishers (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified group photo of men and women in front of Memorial Chapel, 1902? (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Group photo of Wesleyan women in the class of 1892 (Hart, Dilks and Adams) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified group photo of men and women (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified group photo of women, F.E. Willis (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Group photo of Wesleyan alumnae in front of Russell House, 1951 Aug (Box 2, Folder 6)
    View front of photo (JPG).
    View back of photo (PDF).
  - Group photo of Wesleyan alumnae in front of Russell House (duplicate), 1951 Aug (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photo of the Spring Luncheon of the Connecticut Alumnae Association, Emery Studio and Camera Shop, 1955 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Group photo of some alumnae present at the Spring Luncheon of the Connecticut Alumnae Association, 1956 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 6)